In game development we use vectors to
ゲーム開発においては、ベクトルを使用して
find meshes, directions and all manner
メッシュをみつけたり、方角の計算など
of other calculations, which makes them
その他、さまざまな計算を行うため
essential to understand.
ベクトルを理解するのは重要です。
A vector is a line drawn between two points.
ベクトルとは、二つの点を結ぶ直線です。
Vectors also have a length, known
ベクトルには長さがあり、
as their magnitude. Let's start off by
magnitude と呼ばれます。まずは簡単な
simply looking at 2D vectors.
2D ベクトルからみていきます。
A 2D vector is a way of representing a
2D ベクトルは、原点である (0, 0) からみた
point from the origin, the 0, 0 point
グラフ上のある地点を表し、
on a graph, to any point on a 2D plane.
2D 平面の任意の地点を表すことが出来ます。
Since it is from the origin, it has an
原点からみた地点は、
implied direction. It's made up of two
明示的な向き (direction) があります。これは
components, X and Y. These represent the
二つの要素 X および Y から構成されます。
distance from 0 along the X and Y in each axis.
これは X 軸および Y 軸に沿った距離を表します。
In this example our vector goes from the
このサンプルで、ベクトルは
origin to position 12, 5.
は原点から (12, 5) を表します。
The length of the distance between these
これらの点の間の距離は
points is called the magnitude.
magnitude と呼ばれます。
This can be worked out mathematically by
数学的に算出するには
using Pythagoras's Theorem, which states
ピタゴラスの定理を使用して
that the square of the hypotenuse
斜辺の 2 乗は
is equal to the sum of the squares
他の二辺の 2 乗と
on the other two sides.
等しくなります。
The hypotenuse in vector maths is the
ベクトルの数字における斜辺の長さは
magnitude that we're trying to find.
ここで求める magnitude と同じです。
Imagine that there are two people in a field
二人の人がいたとして、
called Charles and Quentin
Charles および Quentin という名前でフィールドにいて
with a lethal vendetta.
武器をもっているとしましょう。
Being gentlemen they've agreed to a
二人の紳士は
pistol duel, but their guns only have a
ピストルでの決闘をすることに同意しますが、 わ
range of 12 units. So can they shoot one another?
ピストルの射程距離は 12 ユニットです。この場合、相手に届くでしょうか？
Let's find out. As you can see
実際にに調べてみます。みてのとおり
the magnitude is the square root of
magnitude はグリッド上での
the sum of the X and Y positions on the grid
X と Y の 2 乗の
squared, which when added together
合計であり、
makes 169. The square root of 169 is 13
169 となります。169 の平方根は 13 なので
so Charles and Quentin will be unable
Charles および Quentin の
to shoot one another, which is excellent
弾丸は相手に届かず
as violence has no place in this tutorial.
平和的にこのチュートリアルが進んで一安心です。
Also, Charles totally had a crossbow the whole time.
さらに、Charles はクロスボウをもっていて
Let's look at another example of using
ベクトルを使用するもう一つの例をみます。
vectors to solve a problem in 2D space.
これも 2D 平面で問題解決してきます。
We've already learned that vectors can
すでにベクトルによって
be used to denote a position in space
原点からみえ空間上の
relative to the origin point.
相対位置を表すことが出来ることをみてきました。
But you should also know that a moving
さらに、移動するオブジェクトには
object has a velocity, a change in
速度 (velocity) があり、
position over time. This can also be
これは時間の経過後の位置の移動量です。
expressed as a vector. In this diagram
これもベクトルとして表すことが出来ます。
Frederick is at position 5, 6
ダイアグラム上で Frederick は (5, 6) の位置にいて
and has a velocity of 12, 5 per hour.
毎時 (12, 5) の速度です。
This means that he will travel in a direction
言いかえると、Frederick は
that is 12 further in the X axis
X 軸方向に 12、
and 5 further in the Y axis.
Y 軸方向に 5 の方向に移動します。
So in order to find his new position after
このため 1 時間後の新しい位置をみつけるには
one hour we'd add his current position
現在の位置に
vector to his velocity vector
速度のベクトルを足して
to discover where he will end up.
移動先の位置が確定します。
17, 11.
位置は (17, 11) です。
Remember that all vectors are expressed
全てのベクトルは
relative to the origin, the 0 point in space.
原点、すなわち空間上のゼロ地点に対する相対位置で表現されます。
And this is no different for velocity vectors.
そして速度ベクトルについても同様に計算できます。
In the same way that 5, 6 is a position
すなわち (5, 6) はゼロ地点に
relative to the 0 position,
対する相対位置であり
12, 5 is a velocity relative to 0 motion.
(12, 5) は移動量ゼロに対する相対速度です。
So whilst he may still have the same
Fredrick の速度がそのままであったとしても
velocity, 17, 11 is Frederick's new position
1 時間後の新しい位置は (17, 11)
vector after 1 hour.
となります。
This is useful in game development tasks
これは予測を伴うゲーム開発タスクに
that involve prediction.
とって便利です。
You should note that the components of
最終位置の各要素は
the final position are equal to the sum
2 つのベクトルの各要素の合計と
of the components of the two vectors.
等しくなります。
5 plus 12 is 17
X 軸において 5 と 12 の合計は 17 です。
in the X axis, and 6 plus 5 is 11
Y 軸で 6 と 5 の合計は 11 と
in the Y axis.
なります。
This also applies to subtraction.
これは引き算も同様です。
3 dimensional vectors work the same as
3 次元のベクトルは 2D と同様に作用しますが
2D but extrapolated in to the Z axis,
奥行をあらわす Z 軸に
which represents depth.
外挿されます。
The X and Z axes make up a horizontal plane
X 軸および Z 軸は水平な平面を形成して
and Y is the direction that points up.
Y 軸は上向きの方向です。
Unity works on a left-handed coordinate system.
Unity は左手系座標軸です。
This means that if you hold your left hand
意味としては、左手において
with your index finger pointed upwards
人差し指を上向きに、
and your thumb pointed out to form an
親指を横向きにして L 字型にして、
L shape, and your middle finger
中指を自分から
pointing away from you then the thumb
遠ざかる向きにしたとき、
represents the X axis, the index finger
親指が X 軸、 人差し指が Y 軸、
Y axis and the middle finger the Z axis.
そして中指が Z 軸を示します。
This hand gesture can be helpful to
この手のジェスチャーにより
remind you of the order of the axes -
X, Y, Z 軸の順番を覚えるのに
X, Y and Z.
便利です。
Given that Z represents depth
Z が奥行きを表すことを前提に
in our previous example, Charles and Quentin
前述のサンプルで、Charles および Quentin は
would have actually been stood on the
実際に立っていたであろう位置は
X - Z plane, keeping in mind that any
XZ 平面であり、
coordinates stated in 3D will be ordered
3D 空間で座標を記述するときの順番は
X, Y, Z. Quentin would have been stood at (0, 0, 0) -
(X, Y, Z) であることを覚えておくべきです。 Quentin は (0, 0, 0)、
the 3D origin. And Charles at (12, 0, 5).
すなわち3D 空間の原点の位置にいます。そして Charles は (12, 0, 5) の位置にいます。
To make things more 3 dimensional
3D らしさを増すために
we could imagine that Charles was on a higher
Charls が高い位置にいると想定してみます。
vantage point. Now stood upon his 7 unit
7 ユニットだけ高い位置に配置してみると、
tall podium, Charles is at position (12, 7, 5).
Charles の位置は (12, 7, 5) です。
The calculation to find the magnitude
Charles および Quentin の間の
of the vector between the Charles and Quentin
ベクトルの大きさの計算は
is the same as in 2D but now features the Z axis.
2D と同様ですが、今度は Z 軸があります。
Unity makes it easy to perform calculations
Unity はこの計算を容易にするために
like this with it's helper function
ヘルパー関数 として
Vector3.magnitude.
Vector3.magnitude など用意しています。
See the documentation link below
より詳細については下のリンクの
for more details.
ドキュメントを参照して下さい。
There are a couple of useful functions
3D ベクトルについてはいくつか便利な関数が
for 3D vectors, the Dot and Cross products.
あり、Dot （ドット積）および Cross （クロス積）といったベクトルの掛け算です。
The dot product takes two vectors
ドット積は二つのベクトルをもとに
and produces a scalar, a single value from them.
ひとつの値であるスカラーを生成します。
To find the dot product of two vectors
ふたつのベクトルのドット積を求めるには
we take their component parts, the
構成要素である
X, Y and Z values
X, Y および Z の値を
and multiply them together to find the sum
互いに掛け合わせて結果の値を
of the resultant values. This is expressed
求めます。
for example as (Ax*Bx)+(Ay*By)+(Az*Bz).
これは例えば (Ax*Bx)+(Ay*By)+(Az*Bz) として表現されます。
With this product you can find out
この積算により
information about the two vectors you've
指定した二つのベクトルに関する情報が得られます。
specified. One example of this is finding
この使い方のひとつは
out whether the two vectors are perpendicular
二つのベクトルが互いに垂直であるか
to one another. If the dot product
確認することです。もしドット積が
of two vectors equals 0, the vectors are
ゼロである場合、それらのベクトルは
perpendicular. In this example we have
垂直です。このサンプルであｈ
two vectors, A and B.
A, B の二つのベクトルがあります。
Vector A is (0, 7, 1). B is (0, 0, 6).
ベクトル A は (0, 7, 1) です。ベクトル B は (0, 0, 6) です。
We can see in this example that the sum
サンプルの中で掛け算をした構成要素の
of the multiplied components is 6,
合計が 6 であり、
which means that the vectors are not
これらのベクトルは垂直ではありません。
perpendicular. If vector A was (0, 7, 0)
もしベクトル A が (0, 7, 0) であり、
and B was (0, 0, 6) then we can see that
そして B が (0, 0, 6) である場合、
the dot product equals 0 and the vectors
ドット積が 0 と等しく、そしてベクトルは
are indeed perpendicular.
確かに垂直となります。
Here is another example of using the
もうひとつドット積を使用する
dot product in this way, this time vector A
サンプルをみますが、今回はベクトル A は
is (4, 5, 11) and B is (-3, -2, 2).
(4, 5, 11) であり、 B は (-3, -2, 2) なのですが、
Multiplying these components gives us
これらの構成要素を掛け合わせると
(-12, -10, 22), the sum of which is 0.
(-12, -10, 22) が得られ、この合計は 0 です。
So these two vectors are also perpendicular.
このため、この二つのベクトルも垂直です。
An example of using the dot product could be
ドット積をしようするサンプルは
when creating a flight simulator.
フライトシミュレータの作成かもしれません。
You would check the world up vector,
ワールド空間の上方向のベクトルを調べて
with the forward vector of the plane.
平面の forward ベクトルとの関係をみます。
If the two were perpendicular -
もし二つが垂直である場合、
if the dot product equalled 0,
すなわちドット積が 0 と等しい場合。
then the plane should have the
平面の
least amount of drag. As the dot product
抗力は最小であるはずです。ドット積が
increases in a positive value
正の値として増加するにつれて
we would know that the plane is pulling up
平面が上向きになってい
and we could add more drag.
抗力を追加すると良いかもしれません。
If the dot product increases in negative
もしドット積が負の方向に増加すると
values we would know that the plane
飛行機がダイブをしていることが分かります。
is in a dive. Unity has a helper function
Unity にはヘルパー関数があり、
to perform dot product calculations easily.
ドット積の計算をより容易に行ないます。
For details of this see the
この詳細については、
documentation link below.
下のリンクにあるドキュメントを参照して下さい。
The cross product is a different way of
クロス積では、ふたつのベクトルを異なった方法で
combining two vectors. Instead of producing
組み合わせます。スカラーというひとつの値を
a scalar, a single value, the cross product
生成する代わりに、クロス積は
produces another vector, specifically a vector
もうひとつのベクトルを生成します。具体的には
that is perpendicular to the original two.
もとの二つのベクトルに垂直なベクトルです。
For example if we took vector A and
例えば、もしベクトル A と
vector B and crossed them then the product
ベクトル B をクロスした場合、その積は
would be vector C, one that is perpendicular
ベクトル C となり、それは A と B と
to A and B. This is mathematically denoted
垂直です。これを数学的に記述するには
by the caret symbol, the 'up arrow' shown here.
キャレット記号 すなわち次の ^ 記号です。
Since Unity's coordinates system is left
Unity の座標系は左手系であるため、
handed so is it's cross product.
これはクロス積です。
Putting your left hand in to the same pose
左手を
as to determine the alignment of the axis
軸を求めるときに形にしてみると、
you can determine the direction of a
クロス積ベクトルの向きを求めることが
cross product vector. In this example your
出来ます。このサンプルでは
thumb and index finger represent vectors A and B,
親指および人差し指はベクトル A およびベクトル B という
the known vectors,
知っているベクトルを表します。
and your middle finger represents the cross
そして中指はクロス積の結果、
product result, C. To look in to the cross
すなわちベクトル C を表します。クロス積を
product in detail we would arrange
詳細にみていくと
our vector A and B components like this.
ベクトル A およびベクトル B の構成要素をこのように整理します。
But how does it work mathematically?
しかし数学的にはどうみれば良いのか？
To work out the cross product we place
クロス積を算出するには
our two vectors next to each other
ふたつのベクトルを隣どおしに並べて
and then repeat this below.
次のことを繰り返します。
From here we can combine the components
この先は二つの構成要素を
one at a time to find the cross product.
ひとつづつ組み合わせてクロス積を求められます。
First we multiply Ay and Bz.
最初に Ay および Bz を掛け算します。
We then subtract Az multiplied by By.
次に Az および By を掛け算した結果を、先の結果から引き算します。
This gives us the X component of
これによりクロス積の X 構成要素が
the cross product. Next we do the same with
求められます。次に同じことを
Az and Bx, and Ax and Bz
Az および Bx、また Ax および Bz で行ないます。
to give us the Y component.
これにより Y 構成要素が求められます。
Finally we do the same again with Ax and By,
最後に同じことを Ax および By、
and Ay and Bx to get the Z component.
そして Ay および Bx で行なって Z 構成要素を求めます。
The good news is that whilst this is a
幸いなことに
detailed calculation, Unity has another
これは詳細な計算でありながら、Unity には
helper function to perform this for you.
別のヘルパー関数があり、この計算をやってくれます。
It looks like this.
このようなものです。
One example of using the cross product
クロス積をしようするひとつの例は
is finding the axis around which
タンクの砲台を回転させる
to apply torque in order to
トルクを加える
rotate a tank's turret.
軸を求めるときです。
Given that you have the direction that the
砲台がすでに向いている方向が
turret is currently facing, and the direction
分かっていることを前提にして、さらに
that it needs to face, you would cross
向くべき方向が分かっていれば
these two vectors to find the axis
この二つのベクトルを掛けて
around which to apply rotational torque.
トルクによる回転を適用すべき軸を求めることが出来ます。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)